A Guide to the Papers of the Buxton, Lea & Marshall Families ca. 1855-1965
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Lea reports on a letter received from Ned Bowen, who has been charged with treating his superior officer with disrespect after a "rupture" with Colonel H.T. Collis (May 7); while in Massachusetts, he mentions his tour of their "braid mill" and the Pacific Mills, which employs 3,200 operatives, chiefly girls (July 13); refers to the "Ketchum failure and forgeries" in New York City, involving over four million dollars (August 15); describes his visit with the Norris family from Baltimore, Maryland, "true blue Unionists," while they were in New York, describing Mrs. Norris as a woman who spent four and a half years feeding, clothing and nursing Union soldiers (August 21); shares the physical effects of the stress of business at the New York dry goods house (August 22); and spends the remainder of his correspondence discussing the buying and furnishing of their house and other preparations for their wedding in December.
Following the marriage of Annie Cabeen and Joseph Tatnall Lea in December of 1865, most of the correspondence is from friends and family to the Leas and include the following topics: Lea's business trip to Chicago, Illinois, St. Louis, Missouri, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, and Louisville, Kentucky (1866 April 18-29); the birth of a daughter, Roberta, to Annie and Joseph Lea (1866 October 26); a description of life in Dresden, Germany (1867 December 15); a description of Rome and Italy (1868 February 27); the birth of daughter, Florence, to Annie and Joseph Lea (1868 July 13); a description of life in Paris, France (1868 July 31); a reference to the wedding of Frank [Cabeen ?] (1879 September 24); and political events in Constantinople, Turkey and neighboring Greece (1879 September 24 & 1881 March 5).
The correspondence of Nancy (Lea) Marshall begins with letters written to her from family and friends while she is on a European tour, 1907, and continues with letters of congratulation and best wishes upon her engagement to Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall from friends, and love letters from Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall, written from the University of Virginia, while she is staying at The Aldine, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, January-May 1911. Marshall's letters contain many references to his work at the University of Virginia during this period.
They married on June 17, 1911, and their wedding photographs were done by Holsinger Studio (1911 June 25). Many of the letters following the wedding are from her mother, Annie C. Lea, when she is in Philadelphia, and her husband, Harry T. Marshall, when Nancy is away visiting her family in Pennsylvania.
Other letters refer to the death of her sister, Florence Lea Fletcher (1911 April); a description of Siena, Italy, and a recent earthquake there in September (1911 September 17; October 31); the birth of a son, Snowden (1912 September); the visit of the parents of Nancy Lea Marshall to the Grand Canyon, Arizona (1913 February 26 & 28) and Pasadena, California (1913 March); an article by Marshall for the Alumni Bulletin about introducing research into the medical school (1913 March 15); a crisis with the nursing staff at the University of Virginia (1913 April 5); the proposal to incorporate Preston Heights into the city of Charlottesville (1913 March 17); an English nurse visited Charlottesville asking for clothes and other items for soldiers in hospitals near Verdun, France (1916 March 8); the visit of University of Virginia alumni to "Bloomfield" during the Centennial celebrations (1921 June); the settlement of the A.C. Lea Estate (1921 June 13; July 25; October 5, 10, 11, 13; November 26; and 1923 October 30); description of a world cruise aboard the S.S. Resolute, especially the island of Bali (1933 March 20); the birth of Polly's baby, Nancy (1947); and the engagement of Katherine Lea Marshall (1950).
The correspondence of Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall begins with letters concerning his work with the United States Coast and Geodetic Survey in Maine and Massachusetts (1892-1894); and a trip to Canada by his friend, Ben Howell Griswold, Jr. of Baltimore, who is also his most frequent correspondent outside of the family and who often comments on the Baltimore social scene and Maryland politics (1897 August).
Other letters include: comments on and requests for his article on Christian Science (1899-1900); discussion of his work in Germany with Dr. Ehrlich by Dr. William H. Welch, editor of The Journal of Experimental Medicine and himself (1901 July 27 & August 12; December 27; 1902 May 18); the assassination of President William McKinley in Buffalo, New York (1901 September 7 & 22); the controversies over the steel industry and the luncheon given by President Theodore Roosevelt for Booker T. Washington (1901 October 21); the New York elections, Tammany Hall, and the new election law passed in Maryland the previous year "with the purpose of disenfranchising the Negro" (1901 November 5); Admiral [W.S.] Schley trial before a Court of Inquiry (1901 October 21, 28; November 27; December 4, 18; 1902 January 6); Supreme Court case involving the rights of citizens of the Philippines, Puerto Rico, and other possessions (1901 December 4); Andrew Carnegie's plans for education (1901 December 11); the Nicaraguan v. the Panama Canal (1901 December 18; 1902 January 29); and Guglielmo Marconi's claim to have successfully signaled a distance of 1,800 miles (1901 December 18).
Other topics include: the death of the father of Harry Taylor Marshall (1902 April 23, 28; May 9); his research trip out west to Montana and Colorado investigating "locoweed disease" in sheep and visit to Yellowstone Park (1903 September 9 & 20; October 18); Marshall's work in the Philippines (1907 May 5); a trip to Maine (1907 August 27); Marshall recommended for the pathology professorship at the University of Virginia by Dr. Welch (1908 February 23; June 17 & attached); Bishop C.H. Brent, Manila, Philippines (1909 September 8); and letters from Nancy Lea Marshall after their marriage while she visits in Philadelphia (1911 October-1913).
The correspondence of Snowden Marshall include several letters describing post-World War II conditions in Berlin, Germany, especially the economic hardships in 1947.
The correspondence of William Dimmock Buxton (1921- ?) begins with letters received while attending the University of Virginia in 1939. He earned two degrees while in Charlottesville, a B.A. (1942) and M.D. (1945), and later became an assistant professor of psychiatry at the University of Virginia Medical School. The majority of the letters during his college days are from family members and friends, especially Robert Winter Reese and Charles Kenton Matheny, both of whom joined the service during World War II. Other friends who write frequently include: Sherman A. Selden (joined U.S. Army Air Force), Sage Smith, Mark H. Congdon (joined Canadian Air Force), Virginia Chandler, C.D. West, Jean Marshall, A.J. Hyde, and Mary Byrd Butterworth.
Topics include: the death of [his mother?] Elizabeth Buxton (1941 June); concern over Germany's invasion of Russia (1941 July 5); Buxton's 20th birthday (1941Oct 10); New Orleans during wartime (1942 March 15); Matheny as an aviation cadet at the U.S. Naval Air Station, Pensacola, Florida, Corpus Christi, Texas, Miami, Florida, and San Diego (1942 April 5, 17; August 9; October 17; 1943 January 27); ideas on instructing daughters (1942 May 11); U.S. Navy Lt. Edward ("Butch") O' Hare gave a speech at Pensacola, Florida (1942 May 15); sexual attitudes of the American soldier (1943 February 6); impressions of Italy (1944 June 8); comments on the "lost generation" (1944 July 21); congratulations on the engagement of Polly Marshall and William Dimmock Buxton (1944 June-September); transfer of William Dimmock Buxton to the National Medical Center, Bethesda, Maryland, and then to Norfolk, Virginia (1945 April 19; May 15-17); and a review of the career of Sherman Shelden during his time in the service (1945 May 21).
The folder of miscellaneous correspondence contains several typed transcripts of letters from an unidentified American soldier serving in a Scottish regiment during World War I (1917-1918).
Identified carte-de-visite photographs in the collection (Boxes 19-20) listed by folder include the following names: in the 1st folder - Commodore James Alden, Julia P. [Aldershaul?], John C. Bigelow, Horace Binney, David A. Deaderick, David Farragut, Stephen Girard, Ulysses S. Grant, Lizzie Hacker, Charlie Heap, Emma Heap, G.H. Heap, G.H. Heap, Jr., Lena Heap, Nettie Heap, Porter Heap, Jr., General [Erasmus Darwin?] Keyes, Annie & Langdon Lea, James B. Leonard, Abraham Lincoln, Chief Justice John Marshall, George Gordon Meade, General Mitchell, Bobby Neilson, Vice Admiral David D. Porter, General Fitz John Porter, John Randolph of Roanoke, Robert Walsh, Bushrod Washington, Daniel Webster, Robert Wharton, Major Winthrop, Mrs. Wister & Alice, and several of political "cartoons" concerning Civil War events and people.
People identified in the 2nd folder of carte-de-visite photographs include: Mrs. Aulick, John Bessonet, George H. Boker, Emma A. Cabeen, Robert B. Cabeen, Sally W. Churchman, Mr. Corbit, Captain Crawford, George Davidson, [Mrs.?] Duhring, Miss Fisk, Louisa Gibbons, [Mrs.?] Gibbons, Eliza & Joseph John Gurney, the Reverend J. Pinkney Hammond (Chaplain in the 19th Regiment of the Pennsylvania Volunteers), Miss Huntington, Draper Lewis, Julia Lodge, McAllister & Brother, Opticians, Mr. McIntyre, Hannah Mifflin, Lloyd Mifflin, Miss Morris, Captain David D. Porter, General Fitz John Porter, Commodore W.D. Porter (with the naval battles involving the Essex listed on the back) Mrs. S.P. Pusey, Mr. R.A. Rogers, Harris Heap Sharrer, Josephine Sharrer, [Mrs.?] Wharton, Bessie White, G. Irvine White, Maggie White, William Whitehead, and a group photograph of Horatio N. Beatty, R. Cabeen Beatty, Samuel Beatty, Kate Bostwick, Annie A. Cabeen, and Lilly U. Cabeen.
None of the individuals are indentified in the 3rd folder of carte-de-visite photographs but they probably include many members of the Cabeen and Lea families, most having been taken in Philadelphia and Germantown studios.
People identified in the 4th folder of carte-de-visite photographs include: John Quincy Adams, William Allen, Rosa Bonheur, Bishop Bowman, Charlotte Bronte, Princess Clotilde, James Fenimore Cooper, George M. Dallas, Millard Fillmore, John Hodgkin, William Hogarth, Bishop Hopkins, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow & children, James Madison, Mrs. O'Sullivan, Tom Paine, John Howard Payne, Rembrandt Peale, Bishop Alonzo Potter, Peter Paul Rubens, John Sergeant, Zachary Taylor, Alfred, Lord Tennyson, John Tyler, the Union League House on Broad Street, Philadelphia, Martin Van Buren, Nicholas Waln, George Washington, and Benjamin West. Also present are examples of art, chiefly Madonna scenes, and humorous pictures of children and pets. Many of the photographs of earlier historical figures and paintings are actually photographs taken of engravings and other art forms.
The three family photograph albums (Box 20) chiefly contain photographs of members of the Lea and Cabeen families and are often identified on the back. Miscellaneous photographs (Box 20) include: photographs of a trip to England, Joseph Tatnall Lea III, Ann Buckley Lea, photographs of places and buildings in Oxford, England (1914), Joseph Tatnall Lea, Kitty & Nancy Lea, and Mrs. & Mrs. Harry Taylor Marshall.
Arrangement
The correspondence in the collection follows a natural chronological order, which is preserved between the various interrelated family groups. There are basically two series: 1) Correspondence (Boxes 1-17) and 2) Miscellaneous Papers, Bound Volumes and Photographs (Boxes 18-22 & Oversize Box P-25).
Contents List
- Correspondence 1855-1960, n.d. (Box 1-17)
  - Cabeen Family 1855-1859, 1861-1862 (Box 1)
  - Annie Cabeen and Joseph Tatnall Lea (Box 1-6)
    1862-1863 October (8 folders)
    1863 November-1864 February (9 folders)
    1864 March-August (8 folders)
    1864 September-1865 February (8 folders)
    1865 March-November (9 folders)
    1865 November-December; 1866 (2 folders)
    arranged chronologically
  - Cabeen and Lea families 1867-1890, n.d., 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Nancy Lea Marshall 1904-1960, n.d. (Box 6-11)
    1904-1911 February (5 folders)
    1911 March-December (7 folders)
    1912 (5 folders)
    1913-1914 April (6 folders)
    1915-1950 (7 folders)
    1951-1960, n.d. (4 folders)
  - Dr. Harry T. Marshall 1890-1914, n.d. (Box 11-14)
    1890-1900 (3 folders)
    1901-1906 (6 folders)
    1907-1913 March (7 folders)
    1913 April-1914, n.d. (3 folders)
  - H. Snowden Marshall 1946-1948, n.d. (Box 14)
  - William Dimmock Buxton 1939-1945, n.d. (Box 15-17)
    1941 August-1942 October (5 folders)
    1942 November-1944 April (6 folders)
    1944 May-1945, n.d. (5 folders)
  - William Dimmock Buxton, Charlotte Buxton, and Julie [Buxton?], while at school ca. 1940-1942 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous 1908, 1917-1918 (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous Papers, Bound Volumes & Photographs 1898-1965, n.d. (Box 18-Oversize P-25)
  - Address Cards & Greeting Cards 1898-1917, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Calling Cards & Invitations 1900-1920, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Financial Papers 1865-1926, 1944, n.d., 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers 1906-1940 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1897-1942, n.d. (Box 18)
    including poetry, identification documents for Dr. Harry T. Marshall, school reports for Hudson Snowden Marshall II, baptismal & confirmation certificates of William Meade Fletcher, Jr., and other memorabilia
  - News Clippings & Printed Materials 1901-1942, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Papers ca. 1921-1965, n.d. (Box 18)
    re "Bloomfield," Ivy, Virginia, and Rugby Road, Charlottesville, Virginia, Homes, chiefly inventories
  - Cash Book kept by Dr. Harry T. Marshall 1908, bound volume (Box 19)
  - Commonplace Book belonging to Nancy Lea [Marshall] n.d., bound volume (Box 19)
  - Diary of J. Tatnall Lea 1865-1867, bound volume (Box 19)
  - Guest Register for "Bloomfield" 1890-1891, bound volume (Box 19)
  - Guest Register for "Bloomfield" 1910-1915, bound volume (Box 19)
  - Guest Register (chiefly) n.d., bound volume (Box 19)
  - Memoranda Books belonging to Dr. Harry T. Marshall with notes on medical cases ca. 1897-1901, bound volume (Box 19)
  - Memoranda Book 1911, bound volume (Box 19)
  - Memoranda Book belonging to Nancy Lea Marshall 1945-1949, bound volume (Box 19)
  - Memoranda Book belonging to Annie Cabeen Lea n.d., bound volume (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook of Engravings belonging to Emma Anderson Cabeen 1843, bound volume (Box 19)
    due to size placed with larger photograph albums in Box 22
  - Carte de Visite Photographs ca. 1860-1880, n.d., 2 folders (Box 19)
    ca. 120 items
  - Carte de Visite Photographs ca. 1861-1871, n.d., 2 folders (Box 20)
    158 items
  - Cabeen and Lea Family Photograph Albums 1864-1886, n.d., 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Loose) ca. 1914-1941, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Photograph Album - "A Bloomfield Retrospect 1896-1897" 1896-1897 (Box 21)
  - Photograph Albums - "A Visit to Bloomfield," Ivy, Virginia n.d. (Box 21)
    numbered photographs in two albums
  - Photograph Album of Trips to Europe and the American West 1902, n.d. (Box 21)
    belonging to Dr. Harry T. Marshall ?
  - Photograph Album of the Marshall Family n.d. (Box 21)
  - Photograph Album of Vacations, and Hunting & Fishing Trips n.d. (Box 22)
    belonging to the [Marshall ?] family
  - Scrapbook of Engravings belonging to Emma Anderson Cabeen 1843 (Box 22)
    placed here with photograph albums due to size
  - Photograph Album of "Bloomfield" belonging to the Lea & Marshall families n.d. (Box 22)
  - Postcard & Photograph Album of Dr. Harry T. Marshall's Trip to the East 1907 (Box 22)
    especially the Philippines, Egypt, & China, including a folder of loose postcards & photos
  - Photograph Album of the Marshall Family and three large photographs of members of the Marshall Family n.d. (Oversize S-55)